This session is about the duties and responsibilities
of directors and we'll also look at some
of the provisions of the Communist and Allied
Matters Act as well as the Nigerian Code
of Corporate Governance and the outline of my
presentation at this session is the duties and
responsibilities of directors, the highlights of the Code
of Corporate Governance as well as guidelines on
corporate governance, the role of the board and
how the board can achieve effectiveness as well
as identifying in effectiveness.
So as we start I think it's important
to define some of the terms we'll be
using here.
Essentially according to the law there's really no
difference between executive and non-executive directors and
so it would be redundant to speak about
executive and non-executive directors from the liability
or responsibility perspective.
Executive directors have day-to-day duties, non
-executive directors on the other hand periodically attend
meetings and have responsible oversight and strategy.
However, if you are looking at the liability
of the board as a whole there is
no distinction between both categories of directors.
So we're going to the specific officers of
the board i.e. the executive, non-executive
and the independent non-executive directors.
So I'll start with the executive directors.
They have day-to-day responsibilities like I
said earlier on to run the organisation and
they typically have contracts of employment that define
these roles.
They're also hired based on their knowledge, experience
and expertise and they're held accountable for those
particular responsibilities.
They have a responsibility to ensure that the
amount of information available to them is also
available to the entire board.
There's usually an asymmetry of information between the
two categories of directors because like I said
the executive directors have a day-to-day
responsibility and they have specific roles regarding the
operations of the business and as such they
have real-time information about the business.
That real-time information is not available to
the people who consider to be outside directors
or non-executive directors and as such the
responsibility lies on the executives to make sure
that all of the information they have is
made available to the non-executives so that
they can take decisions that are robust based
on all the facts.
However, it doesn't absolve the non-executive directors
to say that oh we acted based on
only the information that we had.
They also have a responsibility to demand for
the information that they require in the form
and manner that they require such information as
well as the frequency of such information.
The other category of directors of course is
the managing director who is also an executive
director.
He or she is appointed based on the
skills that he or she has and essentially
that person has oversight of the entire management
team.
The organisations where you have just the one
executive director who typically is a managing director
and for larger organisations you have him leading
the other executive directors.
The third category of directors are the non
-executive directors and they are appointed from outside
of the company.
So they could be shareholder representatives, they could,
I mean they don't necessarily have their own
shares but a lot of the time typically
they are shareholder representatives and as such they
bring they expect to bring independent judgement based
on their own experience from other things that
they're involved with.
Typically one expects that they're involved in either
their own businesses or their own careers or
professions and they bring the robustness of that
experience onto the board.